<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://bpcjk.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://bpcjk.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-12-16T02:09:16+00:00</updated><id>https://bpcjk.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">My passion towards solid mechanics</title><link href="https://bpcjk.github.io/blog/2024/solidmechanics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My passion towards solid mechanics"/><published>2024-11-04T15:12:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-04T15:12:00+00:00</updated><id>https://bpcjk.github.io/blog/2024/solidmechanics</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bpcjk.github.io/blog/2024/solidmechanics/"><![CDATA[<div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blackboard_research2-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blackboard_research2-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blackboard_research2-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blackboard_research2.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="example image" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <hr/> <p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">This page is under construction</code></p> <p>I want to discuss about Solid Mechanics. How it is interdisciplinary with several other fields ranging from linear algebra, optics.</p> <h3 id="what-is-solid-mechanics">What is Solid Mechanics?</h3> <p>Solid mechanics plays an important role in unraveling mechanisms across unseemingly disconnected topics. Solid mechanics intertwines with areas like materials science, physics, geophysics, applied mathematics, and even biology. Interplay of stress (force) and strain (deformation) is different for materials classified under metals, polymers, granular systems. This leads to some magical phenomena such as phase transformations, instabilities. Classification of what type of material also depends on the time scale and length scale of the operations.</p> <h3 id="my-introduction-to-solid-mechanics">My introduction to Solid Mechanics</h3> <p>Another reason I am drawn to solid mechanics is its reliance on and contribution to applied mathematics. Solid mechanics often involves complex mathematical modeling and computational simulations. Differential equations, linear algebra, and calculus are routinely employed to solve problems in stress analysis, material deformation, and wave propagation. The algorithms, and all the computational power that goes with these simulations is very involved, especially while modeling complex biological organs such as cardiovascular systems.</p> <h3 id="delving-deep">Delving deep</h3> <p>Explain atomic structure</p> <h4 id="phenomena">Phenomena</h4> <p><em>Phenomena</em>: Hydrogen Embrittlement, Dynamic Fracture, Buckling of large and thin aerospace structures, Wrinkling, Multistable structures, Shape-morphing structures, Wave propagation, Phase transformations (Plasticity), Mechanics of cells: Actins and Microtubules (Viscoelasticity), Shear-normal coupled structures. <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Will include hand-drawn images.</code></p> <h4 id="widely-studied-materials">Widely studied materials</h4> <p><em>Materials</em>: Metals (steel, aluminum, iron, diamond etc.). Soft materials (rubber, polymers etc.).</p> <hr/> <blockquote> <p>“I like to be buckled, tensed, stretched, wrinkled, dislocated, defected, tortured, bent, and broken. In the end, everything is solid mechanics”- Jagannadh</p> </blockquote> <hr/>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="academics"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[_Stress_ as stress-burster]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Biking adventures in LA</title><link href="https://bpcjk.github.io/blog/2023/biking_adventures/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Biking adventures in LA"/><published>2023-03-04T15:12:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-04T15:12:00+00:00</updated><id>https://bpcjk.github.io/blog/2023/biking_adventures</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bpcjk.github.io/blog/2023/biking_adventures/"><![CDATA[<p>Biking is such an entertaining hobby. Biking gives the feels of flying downhill, catching sunsets, a sense of achievement, and a lot of endorphin rush from that sweat! “LA sucks for biking” is a popular statement among many bikers in Los Angeles. Although, it’s not surprising that notorious drivers from parts of the city are not considerate of bikers, you would be surprised to find some amazing and yet safe routes to explore by bike in a city where living without a car is almost impossible.</p> <p>LA is surprisingly huge and the weather is perfect almost any day of the year. Whether it’s a sunset ride or a sunrise ride, or a snow ride, or a cookie ride, you have all of it here. You get the experience of riding through mountains, beaches, tunnels, rivers, lakes, dams, horse trails, golf courses, observatories, luxury homes, ferries, and whatnot, almost everything. If you are in for some great views, here are some popular bike rides in and around Los Angeles that you should check out.</p> <h3 id="1-rio-hondo-bike-path">1. Rio Hondo Bike Path</h3> <p>Rio Hondo bike path is a one-way 15-mile almost flat bike path starting from Monrovia and ending in Lynwood joining the LA River Bike path in El Monte. The bike path entails a water stream on one side, passes adjacently to San Gabriel Valley airport, golf courses, horseback riding trails, water conservation areas, and many little surprises. While you are riding from South to North, you shouldn’t miss a spectacular view of aircrafts landing, flying, taking off, and missing into the gorgeous San Gabriel mountains.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/biking_blog/pic01_rioHondo-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/biking_blog/pic01_rioHondo-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/biking_blog/pic01_rioHondo-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/biking_blog/pic01_rioHondo.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="example image" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h3 id="2-san-gabriel-river-bike-path">2. San Gabriel River Bike Path</h3> <p>Starting at the foothills of San Gabriel Mountains in Azusa, San Gabriel river bike path is yet another almost flat bike path that offers great and smooth riding, especially for beginners. The bike path is almost 40-mile one way and goes all the way to the Seal Beach.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/biking_blog/pic02_SanGabriels-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/biking_blog/pic02_SanGabriels-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/biking_blog/pic02_SanGabriels-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/biking_blog/pic02_SanGabriels.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="example image" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h3 id="3-pacific-coast-highway-between-ventura-and-santa-barbara">3. Pacific Coast Highway between Ventura and Santa Barbara</h3> <p>What about a ride along the coast during sunset? This has to be the best part of riding on the west coast. While LA beaches have well maintained bike paths with paths being constantly cleared off of sand, the part from Ventura to Santa Barbara along PCH is curved in such a way that the sunset time gradually increases from Ventura to Santa Barbara. The advantage is that you can enjoy the sunset for an extended amount of time if you start the ride at Ventura at right time and pace yourself appropriately. Partly into the ride, start looking back and you would see that Ventura’s side to be dark while Santa Barbara’s side is still bright.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/biking_blog/pic03_PCH-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/biking_blog/pic03_PCH-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/biking_blog/pic03_PCH-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/biking_blog/pic03_PCH.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="example image" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h3 id="4-latigo-canyon-road-in-malibu">4. Latigo Canyon Road in Malibu</h3> <p>Known for its incredibly impressive hairpin bends, latigo canyon road is one of the best climbing routes in and around Malibu. This route gives you the best of two worlds: views from the mountains and the pacific ocean. Start from the pacific coast highway (PCH) near Latigo beach and climb up until the popular Mullholland drive. On a clear day, you can even catch a glimpse of Catalina and San Clemente islands far from the coast. You can mix up your route to start and end at PCH, coming downhill along the Kanan Dume Road. Don’t be surprised if a vintage convertible passes by!</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/biking_blog/pic04_LatigoCanyon-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/biking_blog/pic04_LatigoCanyon-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/biking_blog/pic04_LatigoCanyon-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/biking_blog/pic04_LatigoCanyon.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="example image" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h3 id="5-palos-verdes-peninsula">5. Palos Verdes Peninsula</h3> <p>What about climbing mountains along the coast? Palos Verdes Peninsula offers you stunning views of the Pacific Ocean. The views change as you ride making you wonder if you are in the busy busy Los Angeles area and keep you mesmerizing. Popularly known as the donut loop among the strava users, with an easy to moderate climbing, the route takes you along different segments of Palos Verdes Peninsula. Dolphins might pay you a surprising visit if you are riding early in the morning. Traffic is pretty moderate in this section of the city.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/biking_blog/pic05_PalosVerdes-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/biking_blog/pic05_PalosVerdes-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/biking_blog/pic05_PalosVerdes-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/biking_blog/pic05_PalosVerdes.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="example image" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h3 id="6-mt-wilson-observatory">6. Mt. Wilson Observatory</h3> <p>If you are in for some climbing, take Angeles Crest Highway 2 from La Cañada Flintridge, preferably on a weekday to avoid traffic, ride up to Clear Creek, and then up to RedBox picnic area. Take a right turn at the Redbox picnic area to go all the way to the popular Mt. Wilson observatory. With a moderate steepness (~6%), you can catch snow along the sides of the road during January right after the rain (if it ever!), as well as the snow caps on Mt. Baldy. Make sure you have body warmers while coming down when there is snow.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/biking_blog/pic06_MtWilson-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/biking_blog/pic06_MtWilson-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/biking_blog/pic06_MtWilson-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/biking_blog/pic06_MtWilson.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="example image" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h3 id="7-griffith-park">7. Griffith Park</h3> <p>Wanna see the Hollywood sign? Wanna see the downtown from the hollywood mountains? Want a quick climbing route amidst busy schedule? Check out bike trails in Griffith Park for some urban biking enthralling experiences. Have more time? Ride further up on the popular Mullholland drive nearby the park.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/biking_blog/pic07_Griffith-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/biking_blog/pic07_Griffith-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/biking_blog/pic07_Griffith-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/biking_blog/pic07_Griffith.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="example image" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h3 id="8-san-gabriel-mountains">8. San Gabriel Mountains</h3> <p>Further east of LA, San Gabriel Mountains are an abode for popular climbing routes like Glendora Mountain Road (GMR), Glendora Ridge Road (GRR), Cogswell Dam, Crystal Lake and Mt. Baldy. Start from the foothills in Azusa and bike along Highway 39. Riding until East Fork Road is an easy climb. On the right, you get to see Morris Reservoir and San Gabriel Reservoirs. The dams offer spectacular views most of the year. Just be watchful of the cars while you enjoy the views.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/biking_blog/pic08_SanGabsMtn-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/biking_blog/pic08_SanGabsMtn-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/biking_blog/pic08_SanGabsMtn-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/biking_blog/pic08_SanGabsMtn.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="example image" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3> <p>LA has rides perfect for all levels of bikers. No wonder why several professional bikers train in the greater Los Angeles area. Starting points for most of the roads are within driving distance and could be covered by metro if you are patient. Do check out local clubs that organize group rides. They are a great way to get to know your fellow riders, see the neighborhood from the eyes of locals and find out the little secret lookout spots. Google Street View is also a great source, don’t forget that!</p> <p>By no means this is an exhaustive list of routes/locations. If you are enthusiastic further, check out Gibraltar Road in Santa Barbara, Onyx Loop near Big Bear Lake in San Bernardino Mountains, Castaic Lake near Santa Clarita, Ojai Valley near Ventura, Big Tujunga Dam along Big Tujunga Canyon, Joshua Tree National Park further east. Enjoy spinning the wheels!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="hobbies"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Things that led to several century (100km) rides]]></summary></entry></feed>